(ナルト)終わったな。
It's over...
サスケ 里に戻ってきてくれ。
Sasuke, come back to the village.
そして もう一度
一からやり直して→
Can't we start over and be friends?
友達になれねえかな。
(サスケ)ああ 木ノ葉には戻る。
Yeah,
I'll return to the Leaf Village.
だが 勘違いするな。
But don't get the wrong idea.
えっ？
Huh?!
お前たちと手を組むつもりはない。
I have no intention of joining up
with you guys.
俺は 俺のやり方で
忍世界を変える。
I'm going to change
the Shinobi World in my own way.
"sekkaku hareta kara" tte iiwake o hitotsu houri nage
"The sun's finally out", I shout out an excuse
gareeji kara ikioi makase tobidashita
and fly out of the garage eagerly
mokutekichi wa minami e
I head south, pedaling hard toward the ocean
fumikonde iku pedaru wa umi no hou
chizu nante minai kimerareta you na ruuto wa iya
I don't want to take a route that
I already know without looking at a map
dareka no wadachi wa ashi ga torarete komaru
Following someone else's well-worn path
will only slow me down
isshinfuran ni egaku icchokusen rain wa
The straight line drawn with my heart and soul
boku ni shika mirenai panorama e tsuzuku
continues on toward a panorama that only I can see
konma ni-byou no mirai e ima o kirihiraite ike!
Unlock the present into a 0.2 second future!
tonikaku koge
Pedal until the end
Jiraiya Ninja Scrolls:
The Tale of Naruto the Hero-
Rival
俺の気持は ずっと変わんねえ！
My feelings won't change.
((お前は いったい何なんだ!?
Just what are you?
友達だ！
I'm your friend!
だから お前を→
So that's why I'm saying
(大蛇丸なんかにゃ
やらねえって言ってんだ！))
I'm never gonna let
Orochimaru have you!
友達として
お前を連れて帰るってばよ！
I'm taking you back as a friend.
俺は お前をぶっ倒す。
I'm going to take you down.
ずっと それだけを考えてきた。
That's all I've ever thought about.
いくぞ ナルト！
C'mon, Naruto!
負けねえってばよ！
I'm not gonna lose!
うおっ！
く… くっ！
火遁 豪火球の術！
Fire Style: Fireball Jutsu!
((豪火球の術！
Fireball Jutsu!
ハァ ハァ ハァ…。
あの九尾の事件以来
我ら うちは一族は→
Ever since the Nine-Tails incident,
we Uchiha have lived
under suspicion.
理不尽な疑いをかけられて
里の隅に追いやられ→
We're forced to live on
the outskirts of the village...
どこもかしこも監視の目だ。
このままでは…。
and looked upon with distrust.
If things continue like this...
(フガク)里との折衝は 続いておる。
根気よく議を重ね→
Negotiations with
the village are ongoing.
If we are diligent
in fulfilling our duties,
きっと いずれは よりよき答えを
引き出してみせる 約束する。
we are sure to get
a positive response.
I promise you that.
血気はやる者のなかには→
There are volatile youths among us.
煮え切らぬ
四代目火影を いっそ…。
Ones who cannot stand
the Fourth Hokage and would rather...
(フガク)めったなことを言うでない！
Watch your tongue!
(火影…))
The Hokage...
お前と初めて会ったのは
アカデミーの入学式だったな。
I first met you at the Academy
entrance ceremony.
ああ それがどうした！
So what about it?
あの頃 すでに
こうなることは 決まっていた！
It's been destined that
this would happen, since then!
((ミナト : うちはのサスケ君だね。
You're Sasuke of the Uchiha Clan?
よかったら うちのナルトと
友達になってくれないかな？
Will you be friends
with my son, Naruto?
(フガク)おお これは 火影殿。
どうも。
Oh, Lord Hokage...
そうですな… 友達というよりも→
Hello.
Let's see...
Rather than a friend...
(うちのサスケは 息子殿の
いいライバルとなりましょう))
my Sasuke will grow up to be
a fine rival for your son.
《この子が火影の…》
This is... the Hokage's kid?
アカデミーで 俺は
うちはの長の息子として…。
At the Academy, as the son
of the head of the Uchiha...
((イタチ君が入ってきたときを
思い出しますよ。
I remember Itachi
when he entered...
(さすが 兄弟だ))
You are definitely his brother.
優秀な兄とも比較され…。
I was constantly compared
to my big brother.
重圧に押し潰されそうに
なりながらも→
Even when I thought
the pressure would crush me...
火影の息子である お前にだけは
絶対に負けまいと張り合ってみた。
I was determined never
to lose to you, the Hokage's son.
結果 俺の成績はトップ。
だが お前はドベ。
In the end,
I was ranked at the top.
While you were the loser...
優越感に浸るより 俺は苛立った。
But, rather than feeling superior,
I was annoyed.
なんでコイツが 火影の息子なんだ。
何がライバルだってな！
How could someone like you
be the Hokage's son?
You could never be my rival.
んな昔のこと言われたって
知らねえよ！
How would I know?
You're talking about stuff
from a long time ago!
だが あの日…。
However...
That day...
((犬が！ 誰か！
誰か助けてあげて！
My dog!
Someone!
Someone, please save him!
危ねえ 行っちゃダメだ！
It's too dangerous!
Don't go!
でも…。
助けにいったら→
But—!
If you try to save it,
お前も濁流に流されちまうぞ！
you'll be swept away
by the currents too.
うりゃ～っ！
よ～し よしよし
もう大丈夫だからな。
There... there... You're safe now.
(ハハハ！))
悔しかった。
I was so mad at myself.
俺は あの濁流の前に
一歩も動けなかった。
I stood by the river and
couldn't move.
それなのに お前は
生きるか死ぬかなんて考えずに→
But you didn't even think
about living or dying.
ただ 助けるためだけに
飛び込んで。
You just jumped in and
saved the puppy.
体が勝手に
動いちまったんだってばよ。
My body just moved.
んな 大したことじゃ…。
言うな！
– It wasn't a big deal.
– Don't say that!
俺は動けなかった。
I wasn't able to act.
だが お前は動いた 迷いなく。
But you did,
without any hesitation.
それが… 悔しかった。
That made me so mad.
それから少し経った頃
うちはの不満は頂点に達し→
Then a while after that...
The dissatisfaction among
the Uchiha reached its peak,
暴動寸前にまで膨れ上がった。
almost to the verge of revolt.
((もう あなたの手を
汚す必要はないよ。
There's no need to dirty
your hands any more.
うちはと千住
決して交わらぬはずの→
With the joining of
the Uchiha and Senju,
この二つが手を組むことで→
which was never thought possible...
木ノ葉隠れの里の
平和は守られてきた。
peace has been preserved within
the Village Hidden in the Leaves.
(そして それは 今宵以降も
未来永劫 続くだろう))
And it will last beyond this night...
long into the future.
四代目は みごと→
The Fourth Hokage brilliantly averted
俺たち うちはのクーデターを
話し合いで防いだ。
an Uchiha coup d'état
through negotiation.
火影に対しても
お前に対しても→
My opinion towards both the Hokage
and you changed completely.
俺の見方は 180度変わった。
サスケ。
Sasuke!
お前は
単なる落ちこぼれじゃない。
You aren't just a loser.
俺にはない何かを持った存在だ。
You possess something
I don't have.
本当に ライバルに
なるかもしれないと…。
I felt we could become real rivals.
だが お前は
ちっとも変わらない！
But you... didn't change one bit!
ドベのままで ヘラヘラ笑って！
You stayed a loser,
always laughing foolishly...
俺は お前を認めちまった。
なのに お前は！
And I ended up acknowledging you!
But you—!
知らねえってばよ。
That's not my fault!
俺だって 何とかしようって
一生懸命やって。
I've tried hard to do
something about it.
俺は お前とともに
強くなりたかった。
I wanted to grow strong with you.
競いながら 互いを高め合って
そう思っていた。
Fighting... honing our skills together...
That's what I wanted.
だが お前は突然に！
But all of a sudden, you—!
多重影分身の術！
Multi Shadow Clone Jutsu!
ナルト…。
Naruto?!
いくぞ！
Here I come!
螺旋丸！
Rasengan!
うお～っ！
うわ～っ！
ナルト お前は俺を置いて １人で→
Naruto!
You left me behind
all alone and got better.
先へ進んで
いっちまいやがったんだ。
だから 俺は 必死に食らいついた。
That's why I desperately
tried to keep up.
((千鳥流し！))
Chidori Stream!
大蛇丸から力を得て
ヤツをも凌駕した。
I obtained power from Orochimaru...
and surpassed even him...
それでも お前は 更に 更に 更に
どんどん先へいっちまいやがる。
And yet, you keep progressing and
advancing further away from me.
追いかけるのは もうやめだ。
I don't care about catching up
to you anymore.
だから ここで お前をぶっ倒す！
I'm going to take
you down right now!
二度と先へいかせない。
You'll never get ahead
of me ever again!
俺が 上だということを
ここで わからせる！
I'll show you who's on top
right here and right now!
どうだ！
How's that?
まだまだ。
影分身は まだあるってばよ！
It's not enough!
I've still got my clones, ya know!
それは…。
フッ 仙人モードだ。
That's—!
It's Sage Mode!
仙法 大玉螺旋丸！
Sage Art: Giant Rasengan!
まだまだ！
I'm not done yet!
影分身の術。
Shadow Clone Jutsu!
仙法 螺旋手裏剣！
Sage Art: Rasen Shuriken!
うお～！
ぐあっ！
くっ… まだまだ。
Not yet...
まだまだだってばよ！
It's still not enough!
俺が頑張ってこれたのは
お前が いたからだ。
I was able to aim for
my best...
because of you!
お前を ライバルだと
思っていたからこそ ここまで…。
I was able to get this far
because I thought of you... as my rival!
うぜぇんだよ！
You make me sick!
これしきで なめるなよ
うちはを。 いや 俺を。
Don't underestimate the Uchiha...
No, me!
俺は お前をこえる！
I'm gonna surpass you!
ぐっ…。
(九喇嘛)ヤツは 本気で
お前をぶっ潰すつもりのようだ。
He's serious.
He's dead set on destroying you.
力を貸してくれねえか。
Can you lend me some power?
アイツの サスケの力が すげえんだ。
Sasuke's power is awesome.
(九喇嘛)
わかった。 わしの力を使え。
I got it.
Use my power.
化け狐… あっ いや。
Demon Fox!
Uh, I mean...
お前の名前は？
What's your name?
わしの本当の名前は 九喇嘛だ。
My real name is... Kurama.
SEAL
九喇嘛 ありがとう。
Kurama... Thank you!
やばい。 あの黒い炎は…。
This is bad!
Those black flames are—!
(九喇嘛)ナルト 尾獣玉を使え。
Naruto, use your Tailed Beast Bomb!
えっ 何だってばよ？ それ。
Huh? What's that?
(九喇嘛)コツは 螺旋丸と同じだ。
It's the same as the Rasengan.
終わらせる 俺たちの因縁を。
I'm going to bring this destiny
between us to an end.
ナルト お前を倒す！
Naruto...
I'm going to take you down!
来いよ サスケ。
友達として お前を受け止める！
Just try, Sasuke!
As your friend, I'll stop you!
ナルト！
Naruto!
サスケ！
Sasuke!
(２人)うお～！
うっ…。
お前は 昔も 今も これからも→
You have always been,
and will always be...
友達だ。
my friend.
You're my friend, ya know that?
友達なんだってばよ。
痛ぇよ バカ！
That hurt... you idiot.
ヘヘッ！ 友達の拳は 痛ぇもんだ。
A punch from a friend should hurt!
俺は いつでもどこでも
飛び込んでいける→
You could always jump
into action radiantly, in any situation.
お前が まぶしかった。
Seeing you do that was
so blinding.
サスケ…。
Sasuke...
うらやましかったんだ。
I was so jealous of you.
それだけのことだったんだ。
That's all it was...
だったら それが友達だ。
Then that's what friends are.
＜自来也 : かくして
予言の子 うずまきナルトは→
And so, the Child of Prophecy,
Naruto Uzumaki,
火影となりて
忍の未来を仲間たちとともに→
would become the Hokage,
and with his friends,
forge through thick and thin
疾風怒濤に
駆け抜けていくのであった。
towards a bright future
for the shinobi.
これにて 自来也忍法帳 ナルト豪傑伝
一巻の終わりでありまする＞
Thus ends the "Jiraiya Ninja Scrolls:
The Tale of Naruto the Hero, Part One."
(綱手)ナルトが火影だと？
So Naruto becomes the Hokage...
弟子びいきも いいかげんに…。
Talk about playing favorites...
けど ヤツらなら…。
But those two, eh...?
(自来也)じゃろう？
悪くないラストだろ？
Right? It's not a bad ending, is it?
まあな そうとも言えるが…。
Well... I guess you could say that.
(自来也)綱手 綱手！
Tsunade...
Tsunade!
うるさいな だから
ちゃんと読んだではないか。
You're so loud!
I read it all, didn't I?
うぇっ じ 自来也!?
J-Jiraiya!
(ダン)綱手。
え ダン？
Tsunade...
Dan?
何を読んでいたんだい？
What were you reading?
え 自来也の本は？
さあ？
Hey, where's Jiraiya's book?
I don't know.
I finished reading his novel and...
私は ヤツの小説を読んで…。
まだ寝ぼけているの？
え ダン？
You're still half-asleep, aren't you?
Dan?
(ダン)五影会議への出発時間には
まだ 間があるから→
There's still some time before we leave
for the Five Kage Summit...
もう少し ここで寝るか？
Why don't you sleep
a little bit longer?
夢は もう見飽きた。
I'm tired of dreaming.
(自来也)縄樹
いいものをやろうか？
Nawaki, you want something awesome?
"EROHARA"
姉ちゃんには秘密だぞ？
Keep this a secret from
your older sister.
こらぁ！
Hey!
自来也…。
Ji-raiya...
sonna kimi o nazeka
I don't know why but someone like me
konna boku wa zutto hitei dekinakute
just couldn't reject someone like you
hashitteiru sono senaka o
So I kept running after you
taiyou mitai ni oikaketa
like you were the sun
te ga todokisou na yume wa kachi ga nainda
A dream that's within reach doesn't have any value
zettai ni muri datte iwareru kurai ga ii
I like it better when I'm told it's unreachable
akirameru nante itsudatte dekiru kara
I can give up any time I want
hikihanasaretemo boku wa ganbarou
so I'll keep trying no matter how much we're pulled apart
hito wa doushite ase nagashite kisoiau no ka?
Why do people sweat and fight so hard?
jibun no sonzai o shoumei shitai
I want to prove that I exist
sonna kimi wa kitto
That someone like you has a fear
konna boku niwa nai kodoku ni obieterunda
of being alone that someone like me doesn't have
sono saki niwa daremo inai
There's no one beyond that point
ushiro ni chikadzuku fuan dake
As anxiety closes in from behind
boku ga iru
I will be there
What's going on
outside right now?
『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！ にっぽんの歌』を→
Sasuke?
ご覧の皆さん…。
(２人)こんばんは。
What difference
will it make, knowing that?
ここで 突然ですが 番組から
重大発表がございます。
Hey, Sasuke!
We need to work as a team!
平成23年の10月から
スタートして以来 およそ４年半…。
Team 7 needs to work together
to bring down Madara!
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Itachi's Story - Light and Darkness:
Birth and Death"
その モクハチが…。
We might be the only ones left.
その 引越し先は…。